Ning Ma

Department of Computer Science, University of British Columbia, Canada ning.ma@ubc.ca | Google Scholar | Website

Research Interests

My research interests are in Human-Computer Interaction, Computer-Supported Collaborative Work. I study the *power relationships* and the social-economical contexts of workers with respect to other stakeholders in gig platforms. Particularly, my work attends to workers from marginalized populations including women, financially distressed populations, and rural communities.

Education

Pennsylvania State University, University Park, PA

December 2020

Ph.D. in Information Sciences and Technology

Advisor: Benjamin V. Hanrahan

Concordia University Wisconsin, Mequon, WI

May 2013

B.A. in Mathematics

Publications

- [J3] Hanrahan, Benjamin V., Anita Chen, JiaHua Ma, **Ning F. Ma**, Anna Squicciarini, and Saiph Savage. "The Expertise Involved in Deciding which HITs are Worth Doing on Amazon Mechanical Turk." Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction 5, no. CSCW1 (2021): 1-23.
- [J2] **Ning F Ma** and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2020. Unpacking Sharing in the Peer-to-Peer Economy: The Impact of Shared Needs and Backgrounds on Ride-Sharing. *Proceedings of the 23rd annual ACM conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW 2020). Minneapolis, MN, USA.* [PDF]
- [J1] Johnna Blair, Yuhan Luo, **Ning F Ma,** Sooyeon Lee, and Eun Kyoung Choe. 2018. OneNote Meal: A Photo-Based Diary Study for Reflective Meal Tracking. *Proceedings of American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA '18)*. [Presentation]
- [C5] Benjamin V Hanrahan, **Ning F Ma**, Eber Betanzos, Saiph Savage. 2020. Reciprocal Research: Providing Value in Design Research from the Outset in the Rural United States. *In Proceedings of the Eleventh International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development (pp. 1-5).*
- [C4] **Ning F Ma** and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2019. Part-Time Ride-Sharing: Recognizing the Context in which Drivers Ride-Share and its Impact on Platform Use. *Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 3, GROUP, Article 247 (December 2019), 17 pages. https://doi.org/10.1145/3361128 [PDF][Presentation]*
- [C3] Anita Chen, Chien Wen Yuan, **Ning F Ma**, and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2019. Navigating Ride-Sharing Regulations: How Regulations Changed the 'Gig' of Ride-Sharing for Drivers in Taiwan. *Proceedings of the 37th annual ACM conference on Human factors in computing systems (CHI 2019). Glasgow, UK.*

Ning Ma Page 1 of 4 Updated on: September 2021

[C2] **Ning F Ma**, Chien Wen Yuan, Moojan Ghafurian, and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2018. Using Stakeholder Theory to Examine Drivers' Stake in Uber. *Proceedings of the 36th annual ACM conference on Human factors in computing systems (CHI 2018). Montreal, Canada.* [PDF] [Video][Presentation]

[C1] Benjamin V Hanrahan, **Ning F Ma**, and Chien Wen Yuan. 2017. The Roots of Bias on Uber. In *Proceedings of the 15th European Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work-Exploratory Papers. European Society for Socially Embedded Technologies (EUSSET)*.

[W2] Tang, Joice, **Ning F Ma***, and Dongwook Yoon. Understanding How Customers Attribute Accountability in Food Delivery Breakdowns. 2021. *Joint Proceedings of the ACM IUI 2021 Workshops, April 13–17, 2021, College Station, USA* [PDF]

[W1] **Ning F Ma** and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2019. Supporting Relationship for On-Demand Exchanges in Local Communities. *ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work 2019 Extended Abstract (CSCW 2019). Austin, USA.*

Teaching

Instructor IST331 Foundation of Human-Centered Design (2020 Spring)

Teaching Assistant IST 431 Information Environment (2016 Fall)

IST 413 Usability Engineering (2018 Spring, 2018 Fall, 2019 Spring)

SRA 268 Data Visualization (2019 Fall)

Research Appointments

University of British Columbia

January 2021 -

Postdoctoral Fellow

Understanding women gig workers and invisible work in online freelancing

Pennsylvania State University

August 2016 - December 2020

Graduate Assistant

Understanding Ride-Sharing in On-Demand Platforms: Stakes,

Dependency, and Sharing

Uber Inc. May 2019 - August 2019

UX research Intern

Conducting user studies to inform why do couriers churn from

platforms

Research Mentoring

Ning Ma Page 2 of 4 Updated on: September 2021

Joice Tang, undergraduate research assistant at UBC

August 2020 - May 2021

Understanding how customers attribute accountability in food delivery breakdowns.

Co-mentoring with Dongwook Yoon.

Tabreek Somani, undergraduate research assistant at UBC

February 2021 - September 2021

Making sense of invisible labor with, and for online freelancers.

Co-mentoring with Dongwook Yoon.

Patrick Lee undergraduate research assistant at UBC

February 2021 -

Doppelganger-phobia and identity fragmentation: understanding perceptions and ethical considerations towards interactive digital clones. Co-mentoring with Dongwook Yoon.

Scholarship and Professional Activities

Student Enrichment Fund - Department of IST at Penn State

2018 - 2020

Travel grant of \$1500/year for 3 years

Computing Research Association Grad Cohort San Francisco, CA

April 2018

Women in Computing (funded participation \$1500)

Cornell University Summer School, Ithaca, NY

June 2018

Designing Technology for Social Impact (funded participation \$1000)

MIT Media Lab, Cambridge, MA

November 2018

All Hands on Deck - Open Ocean Fellow (funded participation \$1000)

CHIMe mentoring workshop at ACM CHI

2018, 2020, 2021

The Future of Work (Places) at ACM CHI. Austin, TX

November 2019

Services

Panelist 2021 Cornell University Summer School on Designing Technology for Social Impact

Reviewer ACM CSCW 17', 18', 20', 21'

ACM CHI 19', 20'

Area Chair ACM CHI 21' late-breaking work

Social Event Chair ACM CSCW 21'

Selected Press

"How Uber drivers feel about being managed by machines" in Forbes

May 2018

References

Benjamin V. Hanrahan

Assistant Professor College of Information Sciences and Technology Pennsylvania State University E383 Westgate Building University Park, PA 16802 bvh10@ist.psu.edu

John M. Carroll

Distinguished Professor College of Information Sciences and Technology Pennsylvania State University E319 Westgate Building University Park, PA 16802 jmc56@psu.edu

Dongwook Yoon

Assistant Professor Department of Computer Science University of British Columbia 2366 Main Mall Vancouver, BC Canada V6T 1Z4 yoon@cs.ubc.ca

Chien Wen (Tina) Yuan

Assistant Professor Graduate Institute of Library & Information Studies National Taiwan Normal University No.162, Sec. 1, Hoping East Rd., Da-an District, Taipei 10610, Taiwan tinachienwenyuan@gmail.com